On the 21st of March 1152, four French archbishops
gathered to annul the marriage of King Louis VII
of France and Eleanor of Aquitaine. The union
had failed to produce a male heir in a country
where female succession to the throne
was prohibited. Only eight weeks later,
Eleanor married the man who became King Henry II
of England in 1154. Over the next half a century
she reigned as queen consort and lived to see
two of her sons become King of England. What
role did Eleanor play in this tumultuous
era in the history of France and England?
This is the story of Eleanor of Aquitaine.
The woman known to history as Eleanor of Aquitaine
was most likely born in 1122. There is
uncertainty around where she was born,
but it may have been in the western French city
of Poitiers. Eleanor’s father was William X,
Duke of Aquitaine and Gascony and Count of
Ponthieu. He is known as William the Saint
owing to his untimely death whilst on pilgrimage
to Santiago De Compostela in Spain in 1137. His
premature passing set off a chain of events which
would catapult his daughter onto the centre stage
of European politics in the middle of the twelfth
century. Eleanor was originally named Alienor
after her mother, Aénor de Châtellerault,
from the Latin meaning ‘the other Aenor’,
but her name became adulterated to Eleanor.
Her mother and father had married in 1121.
Eleanor was their first child. A second daughter,
Petronilla, followed a couple of years after her,
and then a boy named William, who sadly died
when he was around four years old in 1130.
Eleanor’s father came from a cultured family
and she was taught history, literature,
astronomy and theology growing up, as well as more
female courtly pursuits like dancing, needle work
and how to play musical instruments such as
the harp. Despite possessing these qualities,
Eleanor’s life, as was entirely common for
a daughter of a prominent medieval nobleman,
was destined to be shaped by marriage and
motherhood. Her position as her father’s
eldest daughter became especially important
after the death of her young brother in 1130,
a tragedy that was compounded by the death
of Eleanor’s mother. What little chance that
her father might remarry and have another male
heir was terminated when he died on pilgrimage
in 1137. With this, Eleanor was placed under
the protection of King Louis VI of France,
who acted as her guardian in her teenage years.
Eleanor had now become an extremely important
person in France’s politics, for the Duchy of
Aquitaine was a large territory that controlled
much of the west of the country. Whoever married
her would acquire control over it.
Although Louis VI was one of Europe’s most
powerful monarchs, the French crown was not
nearly as powerful in the twelfth century as
it would become in early modern times, largely
because of the sheer power and autonomy of the
various dukedoms of the kingdom, such as Burgundy,
Normandy and Aquitaine, that rivalled the power
of the French crown. The roots of Aquitaine as a
distinct region of France date back to the time of
the Roman Empire, when it was known as Aquitania
Prima. It would later be ruled by the Visigoths
and then the Franks, two Germanic tribes that
had invaded the Western Roman Empire and carved
out their own principalities here in the fifth
century AD. Eleanor’s ancestors were granted the
title of Dukes of Aquitaine in medieval times,
although it remained a fiefdom, meaning
that Eleanor’s family held the duchy with
the kings of France as their liege lords to
whom they owed homage. The Duchy of Aquitaine,
at its greatest extent, consisted of the
south-western quarter of modern-day France,
making it the largest and arguably the richest
of the French dukedoms. Whoever controlled it
exercised considerable influence over France’s
politics. It was this colossal inheritance that
Eleanor acquired in 1137. King Louis VI, who now
had Eleanor under his protection, consequently
devised a plan to marry the young heiress to his
son, Louis the Younger, the future King Louis VII.
The only issue from the French king’s
perspective was a condition in Eleanor’s
father’s will that she should retain control over
the duchy until her children came of age.
Prince Louis had not always been the heir to
the French throne, as his older brother Philip
had died in 1131, when his horse tripped over a
black pig that darted out of a dung heap in Paris,
resulting in the 15-year old prince being
thrown violently over the horse’s head and
onto the ground. He was fatally injured and
died a day later. As the second-born son,
Louis had been preparing to embark on a pious
life of religion. The young prince’s religious
upbringing would go on to shape his character
and actions as king. Louis VI was anxious to
make his new heir co-regent quickly after
the death of Philip as his own health was
not good. This was linked to his obesity, and
Louis was known as Louis the Fat. Moreover,
in 1137, the king’s declining health was further
compounded by him contracting dysentery. This
prompted him to dispatch his son to Aquitaine,
along with 500 heavily armed knights. There,
on the 25th of July 1137, Eleanor married young
Louis in the Cathedral of Saint-André in Bordeaux.
Only a week later, Eleanor’s new husband became
King Louis VII of France after his father died.
It was customary for couples from noble families
at the time to exchange wedding gifts to further
seal their union. Eleanor honoured this custom by
giving her new husband a rock-crystal vase that
she had been given by her grandfather, William IX.
The artefact is still in existence today and is
kept in the Louvre Museum in Paris. It is widely
considered to be the only surviving object that
we know for certain belonged to Eleanor.
After their marriage, Louis and Eleanor travelled
to Poitiers, the capital of Aquitaine, where they
were confirmed as Duke and Duchess of Aquitaine.
The festivities were short lived, as word soon
reached the couple that Louis’ father had died and
he was now the King of France. They immediately
rode to Paris, where they were crowned king and
queen consort on Christmas Day 1137. Eventually,
after this frenetic series of events, they settled
down into married life. The young king, according
to contemporary accounts, was devoted to Eleanor,
but she quickly gained a reputation for acting in
an improper manner that was unbecoming of a woman
of her status. This hostility toward Eleanor was
largely due to the fact that she was an outsider,
unused to the customs of the Parisian
court. She was also, it must be remembered,
still a teenager of about 15 years. Whatever
the views of the wider court might have been,
Eleanor’s influence over her new husband became
clear one year after their wedding, when Louis,
along with a small army, put down a rebellion
near Poitiers to protect the Duchy of Aquitaine,
while three years later he undertook a campaign to
capture Toulouse, a city which Eleanor laid claim
to through her paternal grandmother, Phillipa.
Although there is no evidence to suggest that
Louis undertook these campaigns at his wife’s
insistence, it is certain that any campaign
in Aquitaine or Toulouse would at the very least
have concerned her. What we also know for certain
is that Eleanor’s arrival at the French court
did cause some intrigue, as her younger sister,
Petronilla, who had relocated to Paris with
Eleanor, began a relationship with the fifty-year
old cousin of the King, Raoul I of Vermandois. The
couple soon made a public declaration that they
intended to marry, despite the fact that Raoul
was already married to Eleanor of Champagne,
niece of Theobald II, Count of Champagne. In this
instance the queen once again used her influence
over the king to have Raoul and Eleanor’s marriage
annulled on the grounds that they were too closely
related. Petronilla and Raoul were then married
in 1142. Understandably this union greatly angered
the Count of Champagne, who appealed to the head
of the Roman Catholic Church, Pope Innocent II,
who declared that Raoul’s marriage to Petronilla
was in turn invalid, meaning that both of them
now faced excommunication as a consequence. King
Louis, who had previously quarrelled with the Pope
over the state of the Archbishopric of Bourges,
was in no mood to relent to Innocent’s decision,
and so marched on Champagne with an army
and assaulted the capital of the lordship,
Vitry. It was burnt to ashes, while around
1,000 of the city’s inhabitants who had taken
refuge in a church also lost their lives. The war
against Champagne would go on for two more years,
until peace was finally agreed with the assistance
of the French abbot and prominent European cleric,
Bernard of Clairvaux. In a private meeting
with Eleanor he promised that God would
grant her many children if she ceased to
be a negative influence over her husband.
This had the desired effect, as both Eleanor and
her husband soon backed down, and Louis agreed
to return Theobald’s captured lands to him. He
also agreed to cease his opposition to the Pope’s
choice for the Archbishopric of Bourges, although
Raoul and Petronilla remained excommunicated until
Pope Innocent II’s death in 1144.
For Eleanor the church’s blessing seemed to
have paid dividends. She gave birth
to a daughter named Marie in 1145,
who would go on to marry the Count of Champagne’s
son, Henry, in 1164. The episode in Champagne
demonstrates the influence she had acquired over
her husband, but even a monarch as powerful as
Louis could not fight for long against his own
nobles and the Roman Catholic Church. Instead,
Louis determined not long afterwards, with
the encouragement of the new Pope, Eugene III,
to lead a Crusade against the Muslims in the Holy
Land. This Second Crusade was triggered by the
capture of the city of Edessa in the Holy Land by
Turkish Muslim warlord, Zengi, in December 1144.
A year later, on Christmas Day 1145, in Bourges
Cathedral, the King made it known that he intended
to take the Cross and set sail for the Middle
East. Eleanor also took the cross alongside her
husband, the reasons for which are still debated
today. Some historians contend that Louis could
not bear to leave his wife behind in France
and decided that she would travel with him,
though others argue that it was Eleanor who
actually planted the idea of taking the cross
in her husband’s mind. She had a motive for doing
so. Her father’s brother, Raymond of Poitiers, was
the Prince of Antioch, one of the four Christian
Crusader kingdoms that had been founded during the
First Crusade at the very end of the eleventh
century, along with the Kingdom of Jerusalem,
the County of Tripoli and the County of Edessa.
Eleanor’s participation in the Second Crusade
would also ensure a large contingent of nobles and
soldiers from Aquitaine would join the king.
Whatever the motives were, the chronology
is clear. The king, his wife and their army
of fellow crusaders set off from France in June
1147. They entered the Byzantine Empire in August,
where they were received with some suspicion by
Emperor Manuel I Comnenus, who feared what the
influx of hordes of western Crusaders might bring
about in his dominions. Despite this hostility,
Eleanor made a considerable impression on
the Byzantines as they later portrayed her
in accounts as a warrior queen who rode horses
in the male fashion at the head of the Crusader
army. This interest in the French queen, was
reciprocated by the Crusader interest in the
Byzantines. They stayed for over a fortnight in
the city of Constantinople, the Byzantine capital.
Then they received a message that King Conrad III
of Germany, the other great European monarch who
had become involved in the Second Crusade, had
secured a great victory against the Turks. Not
wanting to miss out on the glory, Louis quickly
led his forces over the Bosporus and on towards
the Holy Land, However, upon entering Anatolia, he
learned that the message that had been received in
Constantinople informing the French of Conrad’s
victory was false, and that the German King
had actually been heavily defeated by the Seljuk
Turks at the Battle of Dorylaeum in October 1147.
Judging that they had come too far to turn back,
the French Crusaders joined with Conrad’s depleted
forces and pressed on into the hinterland of
Anatolia towards Antioch. Their journey would
prove to be as difficult as it had been for
the Germans. Whilst approaching the summit of
Mount Cadmus on the 6th of January 1148, Louis
ordered his vanguard to halt and make camp,
but its commanders, one of whom was
Eleanor’s vassal, Geoffrey de Rancon,
decided to continue into the next valley, which
stretched the Crusaders lines and made them
vulnerable to attack. The Seljuks then launched a
surprise attack on their divided camps, resulting
in part of the Christian baggage train being
captured, while hundreds of Crusaders were slain
as they retreated back down the narrow passes or
fell to their deaths in the deep ravines.
Later Eleanor would be blamed by the chroniclers
for the defeat at the Battle of Mount Cadmus,
as it was suggested that she had given Rancon
the order for the crusader vanguard to march on,
splitting the Crusader forces in the process.
However, it should be noted that there is no
concrete evidence to suggest where Eleanor was
during this incident. Over the coming days,
the Turks mounted more raids on the crusaders,
as they traversed the Anatolian mountains,
and eventually Louis was forced to abandon many
of his men and proceed to the Holy Land by ship,
which effectively consigned those left behind
to death from exposure, starvation or attack by
the Seljuk Turks. The King and Eleanor finally
arrived at the city of Antioch in March 1148.
There they were greeted by Eleanor’s uncle,
Raymond of Poitiers, but it soon became evident
that there was a disagreement between the French
king and his wife. Louis was eager to proceed on
to Jerusalem, whilst Eleanor wanted the French to
remain at Antioch to aid Raymond in his planned
siege of the city of Aleppo about 40 miles to
the east of Antioch. Eleanor, for her part,
spent many hours in private conversations
with her uncle for unknown reasons.
Some said she was seeking Raymond’s advice,
whilst others believed he was attempting to
win her support for his plan to attack Aleppo,
whilst some chroniclers even accused Raymond
and Eleanor of starting an incestuous
affair. Modern historians believe this
to be false and the queen and Louis continued
to share a bed together after this period.
It must be remembered that rumours of Eleanor’s
promiscuity abounded both during her life and
following her death. The thirteenth-century
Minstrel of Rheims even claimed that Eleanor
had an affair with Saladin, the Muslim leader
during the Third Crusade forty years later. This
story is completely implausible, as Saladin was
a child living in Syria at the time that Eleanor
was in the Holy Land. Whatever the purpose
of Eleanor’s conversations with her uncle,
they resulted in a disagreement over the Crusader
strategy, as Eleanor wished to remain in Antioch,
while Louis decided they would carry on to
Jerusalem. This was a clear sign of the growing
split between husband and wife. It was possibly at
this time that the idea was floated of a divorce
based on consanguinity, the idea that the pair
were too closely related to have ever been legally
able to marry. However, Eleanor and Louis were,
in reality, much more distantly related than many
royal and aristocratic couples across medieval
Europe. In any event, it would be several years
before the divorce was entered into. In the short
term, the Crusaders marched on to Jerusalem and
entered the city in May 1148, where they were
welcomed by a jubilant crowd, which included the
Patriarch of Jerusalem and Conrad. After finishing
his pilgrimage with prayer at Jerusalem’s holy
sites, Louis embarked on a siege of the city of
Damascus. This enterprise ended after just four
days on the 28th July in failure and retreat.
Moreover, the French resources were now running
low, as was morale. There is very little mention
of Eleanor’s activities during this period. As was
typical with Eleanor’s life, there arose numerous
legends about her activities in the Holy Land,
including one which suggested that she
brought back silkworms from the Middle
East and introduced them to Aquitaine.
After celebrating Easter of 1149 in Jerusalem,
Eleanor and Louis departed by ship towards Italy.
During this journey the royal ships were attacked,
and after narrowly escaping, the ships of Louis
and Eleanor were then separated by a violent
storm. Eleanor’s whereabouts remained unknown for
two months until her ship was finally brought to
port at Palermo in Sicily. Where she was during
that two-month period remains a mystery to this
day. The king and queen were finally reunited in
Calabria in the late summer of 1149, but Eleanor’s
relief was soon dissipated by news that on the
29th of June, her uncle, Raymond of Antioch,
had been killed and decapitated at the Battle
of Inab in northern Syria by Muslim forces.
Greatly bereaved, Eleanor now set off with
her husband north towards Rome, where Pope
Eugenius III had invited the royals to stay in his
palace at Tusculum just south of the city. Both
Louis and Eleanor separately confided in the Pope
about their marital problems during their visit,
but Eugenius adamantly refused to consider
an annulment, as they already had a child
and had been married for many years. Instead,
he blessed the marriage and commanded that it
should not be dissolved under any pretext,
even encouraging the couple to sleep in
the same bed when residing with him.
On the 11th of November 1149, Louis and Eleanor
at last returned to Paris after an absence of two
and a half years. Although they were received by
demonstrations of joy, there was underlying
discontent pervading France at the complete
failure of the Second Crusade. The resentment
heightened the discontent between Eleanor and
her husband. Strangely, their already tense
marriage was irreparably broken by the birth
of their second child, a daughter named Alix, in
the late summer of 1150, as the arrival of another
daughter was a bitter disappointment to Louis,
who, approaching the age of thirty, craved a male
heir to succeed him in the Capetian royal line.
Indeed, he took this birth of a second daughter as
a sign that God did not approve of his marriage.
This view was shared by many of his advisors,
who encouraged Louis to divorce Eleanor and marry
someone less controversial who would deliver him
a son. Louis agreed to initiate proceedings to
acquire an annulment in late 1151, and on the
21st of March 1152, four archbishops of France
gathered at the royal castle of Beaugency on the
Loire River to carry out the separation after
receiving the reluctant approval of the Pope.
This divorce had immense consequences not just
for Eleanor, but for the future of the Western
European balance of power, as by renouncing his
marriage, the King of France had also renounced
his claim to the Duchy of Aquitaine.
Following her divorce, Eleanor became the most
coveted woman in Western Europe. Nevertheless,
Eleanor already knew who she was going to marry.
Indeed, it is likely she had planned it well
before her divorce from Louis, as only eight weeks
after the annulment, Eleanor was again standing
at the altar, this time beside Henry of Anjou,
the future King Henry II of England. Eleanor had
first met Henry in Paris in 1151. Though she was
eleven years his senior, they were attracted
to one another and, perhaps more importantly,
both Eleanor and Henry stood to gain politically
from the marriage. At this time, Henry’s lands
included the northern French provinces of Anjou
and Normandy, while Henry, who was the grandson
of King Henry I, had a strong claim to succeed
King Stephen of England and had been engaged in
a protracted war to try to cement his claim to
the English throne. After arriving at Poitiers,
Eleanor sent envoys to Henry requesting marriage,
then summoned the chief vassals of her lands to
renew their allegiance to her, and to approve
her choice of husband. On the 18th of May 1152,
Eleanor and Henry were married in the cathedral
of Saint-Pierre at Poitiers, much to the fury of
Louis VII, who viewed Henry as a rival. Now, with
the addition of Eleanor’s considerable provinces,
which more than doubled Henry’s holdings in
France, Louis was left vulnerable. What was worse,
Eleanor’s second marriage soon resulted in the
sons that she and Louis had never been able to
have. Over the course of her marriage to Henry,
Eleanor bore eight children, including five sons,
William, Henry, Richard, Geoffrey and John.
The eldest, William, died at the age of three,
but Richard, who would come to be known as the
‘Lionheart’, and John would both inherit the
English crown in later years. The three daughters
were named Matilda, Eleanor and Joan. They would
go on to marry some of the most powerful
men in Europe, including Henry the Lion,
Duke of Saxony and Bavaria, Alfonso VIII, King
of Castile, and William II, King of Sicily.
Eleanor’s unofficial title as, The ‘First
Grandmother of Europe’ is well deserved.
In January 1153, after he and Eleanor had
completed a tour of Aquitaine, Henry set sail for
England at the head of an invasion force, intent
on bringing King Stephen to submission. Henry
was now determined to seize the English crown by
force, and after months of successful skirmishing,
during which Henry took many English towns and
castles and cemented a reputation for bravery
and military skill, many English barons and
bishops urged the two rivals to negotiate. After
the death of his eldest son, Eustace, on the 17th
of August, King Stephen agreed, and in a November
peace conference, he accepted Henry’s claim to the
throne and agreed to recognise him as his heir.
In return, Henry conceded that Stephen would rule
England peacefully until his death. Henry did not
have long to wait, as on the 25th of October 1154
King Stephen died. Thus, Henry and Eleanor set
sail for England, to take possession of their
new kingdom. They were crowned in Westminster
Abbey on the 19th of December 1154, after being
received by a jubilant London crowd, who hailed
the new royal couple as peacemakers, come to
restore order after the years of the Anarchy
that had characterised the reign of King Stephen.
The new royal line established by Henry was known
as the House of Plantagenet. Its members would
rule England for the next 330 years.
Though Henry rapidly established his authority
over England, implementing legal reforms and
consolidating his power, he found his continental
holdings much more difficult to govern,
particularly Aquitaine, whose nobles were hostile
to outsiders. Eleanor consequently had to exercise
an unusual degree of influence over the duchy for
a queen consort. Furthermore, though Henry ensured
he possessed complete control over the most
important matters of state, during the reign’s
early years, Eleanor acted as regent of England on
the numerous occasions when Henry was away on the
continent, running parts of the government in his
absence. As queen, and as a pious woman, Eleanor
was a great benefactor of religious institutions.
She funded the building and restoration of
churches, abbeys and cathedrals in Poitou and
Aquitaine, as well as the Abbey of Fontevrault
in the Loire Valley, which benefited most
from Eleanor’s patronage. Under her influence,
the religious Order of the Abbey grew in influence
and prestige. It was here that Eleanor would
eventually spend her final years and where she was
buried alongside Henry and her son Richard.
In 1168, Eleanor took up residence in
Poitiers, establishing her court in the city,
along with her favourite son Richard. Although
it was Eleanor that initiated this separation
from Henry, the king approved of it and was
not upset or disturbed by the queen’s move,
as having dealt with a large Aquitanian revolt
in the spring of 1168, Henry thought Eleanor’s
presence would help pacify the duchy. There is
much debate as to why Eleanor decided to spend
time at Poitiers. Perhaps her marriage had become
strained. Henry was frequently unfaithful and
Eleanor was in her mid-forties after bearing many
children. It is possible that Eleanor believed
she had done her duty within the marriage and
no longer wanted to take an active part in it.
Furthermore, living in her own lands with a
relative degree of autonomy, allowed Eleanor
to exercise greater power than when she was
with Henry in England. From 1168 to 1173,
Eleanor maintained her own court at Poitiers,
one that has become legendary as the so-called
‘Court of Love’, where chivalric romance was
prominent, and the medieval lyrical poetry
of the troubadours flourished under Eleanor’s
patronage. The queen herself was often mentioned
in the poems of the troubadours of south-western
France at the time, described admiringly as an
elegant and noble woman. However, like so many
of the stories surrounding the life of Eleanor,
her ‘Court of Love’ was almost certainly a myth, a
literary conceit concocted by Andreas Capellanus,
a chaplain at the court of Troyes. He wrote
The Art of Courtly Love in the late 1180s which
describes Eleanor, along with her daughter Marie,
as presiding over a tribunal that made judgements
on intellectual disputes concerning courtly love.
Despite these writings, there is no real evidence
for this ‘Court of Love’ in any contemporary
sources. Furthermore, there is no evidence
that Marie ever visited Eleanor at Poitiers.
Thus, Eleanor’s appearance in Andreas’ work,
owes far more to her reputation than
to her actual actions.
Whilst Eleanor was at Poitiers, pressure was
growing on King Henry II’s rule from his eldest
son Henry. With the treaty of Montmirial
in January 1169, the king divided his vast
inheritance between his three eldest sons. Henry
was to receive England, Normandy and Anjou,
Richard would be granted Aquitaine, while
Geoffrey would acquire Brittany. Furthermore,
the young Henry was crowned as King of England in
June 1170, in anticipation of his succession, and
was dubbed the ‘Young King’. However, the Young
King took after his father in his restless desire
for power. He found having titles without any real
power infuriating, and in his anger a rift began
to grow between the Young King and his father, who
refused to cede any effective political power to
his son. Furthermore, King Henry was increasingly
isolated politically, primarily due to the murder
of the Archbishop of Canterbury, Thomas Becket,
in December 1170 by four of Henry’s knights,
an act which Henry had not explicitly ordered
and deeply regretted, yet one in which he was
still implicated, and which shocked Christian
Europe. Eleanor was amongst those who were
angry at Henry for the incident, and after living
separately for five years she sided firmly on the
side of her sons in the growing family quarrels.
She knew that the more power that they gained,
the more political influence she herself
would hold in western France.
Henry was also coming under growing pressure from
his vassals, especially in Poitou and Aquitaine,
who resented his heavy-handed imposition of
centralised royal authority. After Henry’s
dramatic loss of international prestige following
the murder of Becket, they sensed an opportunity
to overthrow the authority of the English King,
and their growing rebelliousness was encouraged
by Eleanor, her sons, and King Louis of France,
who relished the chance to undermine the might of
Henry’s continental empire. The stage was thus set
for the most dangerous rebellion ever to confront
Henry II. Although Eleanor’s precise role in
the build-up to the uprising is not certain,
it is clear that she was a key player in helping
to form the hostile coalition that confronted the
English King in 1173. In March of the same year,
the Young King escaped from his father and fled
to Paris, where he and King Louis pledged to
assist each other against their common enemy.
Eleanor soon sent his younger brothers, Richard
and Geoffrey, to Paris, to join him in revolt,
whilst encouraging the lords of her southern lands
to rise up. Fearing for her safety in Poitiers,
Eleanor left for Paris too sometime between
the end of March and the beginning of May 1173.
However, on her journey the queen was captured
by men in Henry’s pay and sent to his castle
in Rouen. For the King, her actions constituted
an extremely bitter betrayal and he had Eleanor
confined as his prisoner. Contemporary chroniclers
were unanimous in condemning Eleanor’s treachery,
as her actions violated every medieval
concept of the duties and loyalties of a wife.
Whilst sons rebelling against fathers was
a fairly common occurrence in this period,
it was virtually unheard of for a queen
to rebel against her husband.
The Rebellion of 1173 to 1174 saw little open
warfare. However, many castles were besieged and
lands ravaged as Henry’s sons and the King of
France used scorched earth tactics to decimate
swathes of the English king’s territory. Yet,
despite the strength of their coalition, the Young
King and Louis were unable to effectively organise
the divided rebel groups into a cohesive force,
while Henry II retained the support of
the vast majority of the English nobles,
who feared invasion and instability above all. The
summer of 1173 saw Henry fight tirelessly across
his lands to suppress the rebellion. After a
winter lull, the spring of 1174 saw fighting
break out again in force. Then the rebels’ lack
of unity and Henry’s ceaseless energy saw the
revolt begin to lose momentum after the invasion
of England by William the Lion, King of the Scots,
was repulsed. William was captured by Henry’s
troops led by Ranulf de Ganvill in the summer
of 1174, leading to the English rebels suing
for peace that July. William even acknowledged
Henry as his feudal overlord. This forced
Louis and the Young King to call off their
planned invasion of England. Then, when their
attack on Rouen in August ended in retreat back
to Paris in the face of Henry’s advance, the
rebellion was virtually at an end. For Henry,
this was a great victory against considerable
odds. It restored his international reputation
from the tarnished state it had been in
after the death of Saint Thomas Becket.
The outcome of these events was that a peace was
reached on the 30th September 1174 between Henry
and his sons at Montlouis. The King generously
gave money and castles to his remorseful sons,
but he did not cede any real political power.
Unusually, he inflicted a distinct revenge on
Eleanor. While Henry proclaimed a general amnesty
for all those who had risen up against him, this
was not extended to his wife. After travelling
to England with Henry on the 8th of July 1174,
Eleanor was placed under house arrest. For
the remainder of Henry’s life, until 1189,
she would remain a virtual prisoner and was only
permitted limited contact with her children. The
King dealt with Eleanor so discreetly that very
little is known about her life during these years.
She was mostly kept under detention at Winchester
Castle. Although Eleanor lived in fairly luxurious
surroundings here, the king ensured she was
completely cut off from the outside world, as
he had first-hand proof of how dangerous Eleanor
could be. The king then enjoyed several years of
peace before the Young King revolted again in
the early 1180s. Richard’s harsh suppression
of rebellious barons and the ruthless enforcement
of his authority in Aquitaine, which he now ruled
in Eleanor’s absence, caused his bitter vassals
to look to the Young King to challenge Richard.
And so the impetuous Young Henry joined with
the Barons of Aquitaine and invaded Richard’s
territory in 1182. When Henry II stopped his
eldest son’s allowance in response, the Young
King formed a mercenary band and raided and looted
territories throughout southern France. However,
in June 1183, the Young King fell violently
ill with dysentery and died at the age of 28.
After the shock death of the Young King, from
the late summer of 1183, Eleanor was allowed
greater freedom, resuming her place as Queen and
occasionally appearing at Henry’s side in public,
but there were no obvious signs that the
couple’s personal estrangement had ended.
By 1189, Henry had reached the age of 56.
Although he was twelve years younger than Eleanor,
a lifetime of relentless activity had left him
suffering from numerous health problems, including
a bleeding ulcer. Thus, only six years after the
death of Young Henry, the King died on the 6th of
July 1189 in his castle at Chinon and was buried
at the nearby Fontevraud Abbey. And so, Richard I
was crowned King of England in Westminster Abbey
on the 3rd September 1189, following his father’s
death, in front of an enthusiastic gathering. One
of his first acts as king was to formally order
the release of Queen Eleanor from captivity.
Despite having been a prisoner for 15 years,
Eleanor emerged with ferocity onto the European
political scene at the age of 67. For the
remaining 15 years of her life, she would play a
more influential political role than ever before,
as the queen was able to exert far more influence
over her children, than she did over her late
husband. With Richard in Aquitaine, Eleanor set
about drumming up support for her son in England,
a country that Richard had barely visited. Upon
travelling to Westminster, the Queen received
oaths of loyalty from the lords of England on
behalf of the King. In addition, Eleanor passed
a host of laws, in an attempt to endear the
English people to their new king, including
ordering the release of vassals who had rebelled
against Henry II. The 31-year-old Richard, sailed
to Portsmouth on the 13th of August, where, thanks
largely to Eleanor’s efforts, he was greeted with
great public enthusiasm. Nonetheless, Richard the
Lionheart, who was a French lord by temperament,
had very little interest in administering
his new domain. Rather he immediately threw
himself into preparing for the project that
dominated his imagination – the Third Crusade.
On the 2nd of October 1187 the Muslims led by
their brilliant military commander, Saladin,
had occupied Jerusalem and massacred the Knights
Templar, causing the leaders of Western Europe,
urged on by Popes Urban III and Clement III, to
initiate a new crusade. After implementing heavy
taxes on the English people and the nobility
to pay for his supplies, Richard departed
from England in December 1189 for France with the
ultimate aim of making his way to the Holy Land.
In his absence he left Eleanor unofficially
in charge of the English government.
Her imprisonment had made Eleanor increasingly
pious, yet her tenacious energy had not been
eroded in the slightest, and in Richard’s
absence she transacted the business of
state using her own seal on official documents,
demonstrating the qualities of a benevolent ruler,
and greatly impressing contemporary chroniclers.
Eleanor also had to deal with the intrigues of
Richard’s younger brother, John, who was furious
at Richard’s intention to name his four-year-old
nephew, Arthur of Brittany, as his heir He
travelled up and down England in an attempt
to gain support amongst the English. Philip II of
France had left the Crusade due to illness. Upon
his return to France in 1191, Eleanor realised
that the King presented another threat to
Richard’s authority in Europe, and after John and
Philip formed an alliance in early 1191, the Queen
spent considerable time and energy, thwarting the
intrigues of these two princes during Richard’s
absence. Upon hearing in February 1192 that John
was preparing to cross the channel with an army to
join with Philip, Eleanor travelled to England
from Normandy to stop him. After making every
English magnate swear a new oath of fealty
to Richard, Eleanor threatened to confiscate
John’s castles and estates if he defied her.
He backed down initially, but as the crusaders
began arriving home in the winter of 1192, having
failed to recapture Jerusalem, Eleanor received a
letter from the Holy Roman Emperor, Henry VI,
stating that Richard had been taken captive by
the Emperor’s cousin, Duke Leopold of Austria,
whom he had offended whilst on crusade.
Leopold’s overlord, Henry VI, was a ruthless
man, who was an enemy of the Plantagenets after
Henry II had supported his great rival, Henry the
Lion, Duke of Saxony. Leopold now sought to exact
revenge on his son and heir. After taking control
of the prisoner, Henry demanded an extortionate
ransom of 100,000 silver marks, a sum equivalent
to twice the annual revenue of England. With her
customary vigour, Eleanor set to work raising the
King’s ransom, whilst keeping the kingdom united
and again blocking John’s attempts to claim the
throne. Though England was already financially
exhausted after the crusade, Eleanor imposed a
levy demanding a quarter of every person’s annual
income, as well as extracting wealth from churches
and abbeys; nor were these efforts limited to
England, as Eleanor sent officials into Anjou and
Aquitaine to collect ransom money. With the money
raised, Eleanor herself set out for Germany in
December 1193, and was received on 2nd February
1194 by the Emperor at his court in Mainz.
However, Henry VI then announced that Philip
and John had offered him an even greater ransom
sum, to hand over Richard to the King of France,
and it was only after 48 hours of negotiations
that Eleanor and Richard’s German allies
persuaded the Emperor to release the King.
With the triumphant return of the crusader
king to England on the 12th of March 1194, all
rebellious support for John was crushed. Richard
quickly re-established his authority, forgiving
his troublesome younger brother, whom he did not
regard as a serious threat. John was obedient to
his brother for the remainder of his reign.
The same could not be said of King Philip
of France. During the final five years of
Richard’s short reign, the English king was
engaged in a bitter struggle with Philip,
tirelessly defending his territories against
the aggressive ambition of the French King,
Eleanor meanwhile, lived at the Abbey of
Fontevrault for the final years of Richard’s
reign, looking toward the salvation of her soul
and death, as by 1199 the Queen was 77 years old.
Richard’s conflict with Philip was brought to an
end on the 13th of January 1199 when a five-year
truce was concluded without the Lionheart ceding
any of his territory to Philip. Richard’s reign
would end less than three months later when he was
struck by an arrow whilst besieging the castle of
a rebellious Aquitanian vassal. He died of his
wound on the 6th of April 1199 at the age of 41
after declaring John as his heir. Eleanor was at
the bedside of her beloved son when he perished,
and she saw to it that he was buried at the Abbey
of Fontevrault, at the foot of his father’s tomb.
Of immediate importance to Eleanor, following
Richard’s death, was to ensure that her son John
received his inheritance, as the ever troublesome
Philip II proclaimed Richard’s nephew Arthur of
Brittany, who was residing with the French King
in Paris, as the rightful heir to his empire,
leading to numerous vassals in the province of
Anjou declaring themselves for Arthur. The Queen
responded by ordering the devastation of the lands
of any vassal disloyal to her son, and Arthur’s
support in Anjou was soon quashed. Furthermore,
Eleanor embarked on a tour of her southern lands
to consolidate support for John in Aquitaine and
Poitou. When John was crowned as King of England
in May 1199 his continental holdings were secure,
thanks largely to the actions of his mother.
In late 1199, Philip concluded a truce with
John, recognising the English King as Richard’s
successor and providing for the marriage of
Philip’s heir to one of John’s Castilian nieces,
the daughters of his sister Eleanor. It was
decided that Queen Eleanor should travel to
Castile to select one of the princesses and
convey them back to France, a strenuous journey
for a woman in her late seventies, yet Eleanor
welcomed the opportunity to see her daughter for
the first time in 30 years. Following the truce,
Eleanor set off from Poitiers and was ambushed and
captured just south of the city by a rebellious
vassal, Hugh de Lusignan, who demanded she grant
him the title of Count of La Marche in return for
her release. She agreed after deciding that the
Castilian marriage was of greater importance
than a disputed fiefdom. She then crossed the
Pyrenees and travelled onwards to the court of
Castile in late January 1200. There she chose
16-year-old Blanche to marry the French heir,
a choice that would prove to be a wise one, as
Blanche of Castile would ultimately become almost
as formidable a queen as her grandmother, keeping
France stable during the minority of her son, the
future Saint, Louis IX. Eleanor arrived back in
southern France in April, where she soon made her
final impact on the European political stage after
war again broke out between John and Philip. The
queen immediately declared her support for John,
outraged at Arthur of Brittany’s invasion of
Poitou to claim the province for himself. In
late July, Eleanor set out from Fontevrault with a
military escort to install herself at Poitiers to
deter Arthur’s advance. She stopped on the way to
lodge at the castle of Mirabeau some twenty miles
north-east of Poitiers. However, Arthur learned
of her whereabouts, and then besieged the castle,
intending to take the old queen hostage.
Instructing her men to defend the fortress,
Eleanor smuggled out a message to John,
requesting aid. Upon receiving the letter,
the King immediately marched to the castle,
arriving on August 1st, and in a surprise attack
the besiegers were overcome, Arthur captured, and
Eleanor freed and escorted to safety. In her final
defining act, Eleanor had helped John to achieve
the greatest military victory of his reign.
Returning to Fontevrault Eleanor took the veil and
became a nun for the remainder of her life. She
died on the 1st of April 1204 at the age of 82 and
was buried in between her husband and her son.
During her final years, the old Angevin empire was
falling apart around her as the ineffectiveness of
King John was ruthlessly exploited by Philip of
France. By 1205 he had taken control of Normandy,
Anjou and Poitou. Eleanor’s immediate legacy
was marred, by the fall of her empire,
and medieval thirteenth-century chroniclers
ensured her reputation was dominated by the
rumours of the scandals of her youth, rather
than the wise and pious rule that defined her
later years. In reality, the collapse of John’s
continental holdings following Eleanor’s death
demonstrates her skill in managing the political
and military in France while she was alive. It
was only when Eleanor withdrew from political
life that the empire she had spent so much of
her life working to uphold collapsed. The fact
that the life of Eleanor of Aquitaine has been,
and continues to be, surrounded by legend and
myth, speaks to the fierce grip she held on the
imagination of medieval Europe. She has gone from
being portrayed as an evil and scandalous queen
throughout the nineteenth century, to a romantic
heroine in the twentieth. Even today her failings
and her achievements are often exaggerated.
Eleanor had a remarkably long career as a
political figure in Europe and an important
impact on history, in an era when women were
so often relegated to a servile role. Indeed,
there are not many more influential figures in
the history of medieval Europe. As the nuns of
Fontevrault wrote after she died, “she surpassed
almost all the queens of the world.”
What do you think of Eleanor of Aquitaine?
Was she really a charming seductress, using her
attractiveness to the greatest degree possible,
or was she an intelligent stateswoman primarily
motivated by fierce loyalty to her children?
Please let us know in the comment section, and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching.